A. Mark Datz Papers
A. Mark Datz Papers
1916-1969
Datz, A. Mark (Abraham Mark), 1889-1969
9.0 linear ft.
Correspondence (1926-1965), limited to a very few letters; exhibition catalogs and announcements for one-man and group shows (1926-1963); 12 journals (1943-1969); photographs and negatives of Datz's work; 80 etchings on 77 copper plates; and clippings (1916-1941).
148928
Biographical History
American Jewish painter, etcher. Born in Russia 1889, emigrated to the United States in 1903.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Boxes 2-6 are VERY HEAVY. Handle with care.
Spanning 1916 through 1969, the A. Mark Datz Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, memorabilia, and writings of the American painter and etcher (1889-1969). A Russian Jew by birth, Abraham Mark Datz emigrated to the United States in 1903. The collection provides insight into his Jewish heritage as well as his personal life and artistic career.
Arranged chronologically, the Correspondence is limited to a few incoming letters, predominantly from the 1960s. Correspondents include art-related institutions (American Federation of Arts, Birmingham Museum of Art, Evansville Museum of Arts and Science), photographer Hans Namuth, and writer Richard C. Rothschild.
Artwork encompasses copper and zinc plates, negatives and photographs of Datz's paintings, and a reproduction of "Martha Pollak" incorporated into a Carnegie Recital Hall announcement. Despite occasional gaps in Datz's numbering system and the presence of a few unnumbered etchings, Copper and zinc plates are arranged numerically. There is a total of 80 etchings on 77 plates, 3 of which bear images on both sides. An alphabetical index of etching titles follows the box list. Photographs, primarily undated, are organized alphabetically by titles supplied by Datz, and followed by a number which are untitled.
Memorabilia includes one photograph of Datz, printed material, and a typescript review by Richard C. Rothschild. Printed material contains newspaper clippings (1916-1941), exhibition catalogs and announcements of group (1928-1963) and one-man shows (1926-1946), in addition to several art periodical reviews (1936-1952).
Writings consists of twelve journals (1943-1969) which, with few exceptions, Datz updated daily.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Datz, A. Mark (Abraham Mark), 1889-1969.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists -- Diaries.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Etchers -- United States.; Etching -- Technique -- Specimens.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Diaries.; Negatives (photographs); Photographs.; Reviews (documents); Artists.; Etchers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - A-Z, 1926-1965; 1 folder (Box 1)
    See also Selected Index to Correspondence
- Artwork
  - Copper and zinc plates, See also Alphabetical Index of Etchings
    - Numbers 2-5, 7-13, 15, 17-18, 15 etchings, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - Numbers 20-21, 23-26, 28-29/30, 30-31, 33/34, 36-38, 16 etchings, 14 folders (Box 3)
    - Numbers 39, 43, 50, 55-59, 61-62, 65-66, 68-69, 14 etchings, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - Numbers 70, 74, 76-81, 83-86, 12 etchings, 11 folders (Box 5)
    - Numbers 87-93, unnumbered, some of the unnumbered have titles, some have no numbers or titles; 14 etchings, 14 folders (Box 6)
    - Numbers 19, 40, 47, 54, 73 (Oversize 1)
    - Numbers 75, 82, unnumbered, some of the unnumbered have titles, some have no numbers or titles (Oversize 2)
  - Drawings
    - Pen and ink, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Pen and ink (Oversize 3)
    - Pencil, pen and ink, pastels (Box 7)
    - Pencil (Oversize 3)
    - Sketchbooks, 3 volumes (Box 7)
  - Negatives
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 72 items (Box 7)
  - Photographs of paintings
    - By title, A-S, 1959-1963; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - By title, T-Y, 1959-1963 (Box 8)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 8)
  - Reproductions
    - Martha Pollak, 1945; 1949,; 1956; paintings of Pollak, used by her in her recital programs at Carnegie Hall (Box 8)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs, 1962; undated (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook of photographs, undated (Box 8)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1916-1941; undated (Box 8)
    - Exhibition catalogs, announcements
      - Group shows, 1928-1935 (Box 9)
      - Group shows, 1936-1963; undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - One-man shows, 1926-1946 (Box 9)
    - Reviews, 1936-1952 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1926; Yiddish publication "Teater Shtern" (Theater Star) with article about Datz (Box 9)
  - Reviews (typescript), undated (Box 9)
- Writings
  - Journals, 1943; 1947,; 1948,; 1952-1953; 4 volumes (Box 10)
  - Journals, 1954-1957; 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - Journals, 1958-1962; 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Journals, 1962-1965; 2 volumes (Box 13)
  - Journals, 1965-1969; 2 volumes (Box 14)
Alphabetical index of etchings
Americana (#54)
Anticipation (#33 or #34)
The Belfry (#12)
Birds Over the Reservoir (#82)
Bookplate (Richard C. Rothschild) (#66)
Boy in Bed (unnumbered, Box 10)
Boy with Mandolin (#31)
Boys with Kite (#18)
Bride (#5)
Chinese Lantern (#30)
City Retreat (#56)
Day of Atonement (#93)
Day of Rest (#47)
Desert Mountains (#91)
Evening (#40)
Excavation (#83)
Exquisite Self (#79 or #80)
Field Day (#75)
Fountain at Bryant Park (#37)
Gargoyle and Birds (#58)
Golfers (#57)
Harlem River Bridge (#3)
The Harvester (#10)
Hillside (#77)
Hudson River Piers (#13)
Humid Day (#88)
Hungry Eyes (#87)
Impulses (#73)
Impulses (#74)
Iron Age (#36)
A Man Descending (#50)
(Miniature with Smoke Stack) (#84)
Mothers Prayer (#68)
Needy People (#9)
Nude (#29)
The Old Pride (#90)
On the Roof (#8)
Oracle Road (#89)
The Organ Grinder (unnumbered, Box 10)
The Pagoda (#70)
Palm Trees (#92)
The Park Vendor (#15)
Peace on the Roof (#61)
Pelham Bay Bridge (#26)
Picnickers (#2)
Portrait of an Artist (#33 or #34)
Prancing Horse (#7)
Prelude (unnumbered, Box 11)
Promenade (#38)
Reflections (#69)
Riverdale (#28)
Riverside or Towers (#19)
Riverside Park (#17)
Roman Celebration (#11)
Sanctuary Hill (#55)
The Sculptress (#25)
Self Portrait (#62)
Self Portrait (#76)
Silent Moments (#59)
The Shrine (#79 or #80)
The Shrine (#85)
Sitting Figure (#20 or #21)
Sleeping Outdoors (#10)
Snowballs (#43)
Solitary Mood (#81)
Speakeasy (#20 or #21)
Spring (#65)
Street Scene (#24)
Towers or Riverside (#19)
Van Cortlandt Lake (#78)
Waiting for Lefty (#39)
Whisper & Glances (#86)
Woman Reading (#30)
Woman Reading on the Roof (unnumbered, Box 10)
Woman with Bird (#23)
Woman with Fruit (#4)
Selected index to correspondence
American Federation of Arts 1962 Feb. 6
Birmingham Museum of Art1962 May 11 (to Dorothy Paris) 1962 June 13 (to Dorothy Paris)
Evansville Museum of Arts and Science 1961 Oct. 5
Namuth, Hans 1963 Oct. 10
National Historic Shrines Foundation, Inc. 1965 Feb. 17
Rothschild, Richard C. 1940 Feb. 2